Guide to the Zurcher v. The Stanford Daily Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Zurcher v. The Stanford Daily records
1969-1999
SC0580
Stanford Daily.
1.5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of The Stanford Daily, 1999.
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Historical Note
On April 12, 1971, Palo Alto police officers obtained a warrant to search the offices of the student newspaper The Stanford Daily for photographic evidence of the April 9th Stanford University Hospital sit-in, in which property was damaged and nine officers injured. It was the first known use of a search warrant in an American newspaper office. On May 12, The Daily filed a law suit against James Zurcher, chief of police, and other officers claiming that the search was in violation of First, Fourth and Fourteenth Amendment rights. The case attracted national attention and became a test of the freedom of the press. Although lower courts upheld the case it was later reversed by the U. S. Supreme Court.
Scope and Content
These records, created by The Stanford Daily as well as their attorneys (Jerome B. Falk, Jr. and Robert H. Mnookin of the Howard, Prim, Rice, Nemerovski, Canday & Pollack law firm and Anthony G. Amsterdam of the Stanford Law School), include correspondence, 1971-80; legal documents (depositions, motions, petitions, briefs, and others), 1974-1978; a notebook on the case's oral argument kept by attorney Jerome B. Falk; transcripts from the trial, 1971-72; and clippings and news articles, 1971-1978. There is also a trial transcript from an earlier case (testimony of Mark Weinberger in People v. Steven Kessler, Oct. 23, 1969) involving The Stanford Daily photographers covering a demonstration.
Correspondents include attorneys Anthony G. Amsterdam, Robert H. Mnookin, Jerome B. Falk, Jr., and Franklin R. Garfield; Daily editors Felicity Barringer, Edward H. Kohn, and Fred Mann; and Peter G. Stone and Marilyn D. Norek, attorneys for Palo Alto.
Access Terms
Falk, Jerome B.; Kohn, Edward H.; Mann, Frederick G.; Mnookin, Robert H.; Norek, Marilyn D.; Stone, Peter G.; Taubman, Felicity Barringer.; Freedom of the press--Cases.--United States; Freedom of the press--United States.; Stanford Daily.
Collection Contents
- Records
  - Appeal memos (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appeal memos (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appellees' Opening Brief - draft (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Appellees' Opening Brief, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Attorneys' fees (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Audit letters, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1972 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1972 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1973 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1973 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1974 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1974 Jun-Dec (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1976 Sep (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1976 Oct-1977 May (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1977 Jun-Dec (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and clippings re legal bills, 1972-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Depositions: Jerome B. Falk, Jr., Franklin B. Garfield, 1974; 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous legal documents (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Notes for oral argument, JBF (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Pleadings: (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1. Motion of Joseph Berman, Charles Lyle and Robert Litterman to Quash Subpoenas Duces Tecum; Memorandum of Points and Authorities in Support Thereof
    - 2. Motion for continuance of Hearing on Motion to Quash Subpoenas Duces Tecum; Affidavit in Support Thereof
  - Pleadings: (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 91. Notice of Joining of Co-Counsel, Feb 14, 1977
    - 92. Petition for Rehearing by Defendants-Appellants Zurcher, Bondander, Deisinger, Martin, and Peardon and Suggestion that Rehearing be in Banc, Feb 14, 1977
    - 93. Petition for Rehearing and Suggestion for Rehearing In Banc on Behalf of Appellants Bergna and Brown, Feb 16, 1977
    - 94. Order of U.S. Court of Appeals rejecting petitions for rehearing and rehearing en banc, (March 28, 1977)
    - 95. Motion for Stay of Mandate pending Application for Certiorari, Apr 1, 1977
    - 96. Memorandum in Opposition to Motion for Stay of Mandate, Apr 4, 1977
    - 97. Reply to Memorandum in Opposition to Motion for Stay of Mandate, Apr 8, 1977
    - 98. Order Staying Issuance of Mandate (filed, 12-Apr-77
    - 99. Motion for Extension of Stay of Mandate, Apr 18, 1977
  - Pleadings: (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 100. Memorandum in Opposition to Motion for Extension of Stay of Mandate, Apr 19, 1977
    - 101. SUPREME COURT OF U.S.: Petition for a Writ of Certiorari to the U. S. Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit (served 4/25/77; received 4/26/77)
    - 102. Letter to Clerk of Supreme Court in response to Petition for Writ of Certiorari, (May 2, 1977)
    - 103. Letter to clerk of Supreme Court by opposing counsel, (May 4, 1977)
    - 104. Appearance form before Supreme Court of U.S. (mailed, May 6, 1977)
    - 105. SUPREME COURT OF U. S.: Petition for Writ of Certiorari [filed by petitioners Bergna and Brown] (served received, May 13, 1977; May 16, 1977)
  - Pleadings: (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 106. Letter to Clerk of Supreme Court by respondents re filing no response to petition for certiorari, (May 20, 1977)
    - 107. Appearance form before Supreme Court of U. S. (re second petition for Certiorari) mailed), (May 25, 1977
    - 108. Counsel for City Attorney, City of Palo Alto's Appearance Form before Supreme Court of U. S. (received, July 6, 1977)
    - 109. Brief for Respondents in Opposition (U. S. Supreme Court), (July 29, 1977)
  - Pleadings: (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 131. Notice of denial of motion of Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press to argue, Jan 16, 1978
    - 132. Respondents' Reply to the Brief of the United States as Amicus Curiae, Jan 16, 1978
    - 133. Petitioners' Reply to the Brief of the United States as Amicus Curiae, Jan 24, 1978
  - Pleadings: (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 134. U.S. SUPREME COURT OPINION (decided, May 31, 1978)
    - 135. Petition for Rehearing, (June 23, 1978)
    - 136. Motion of the American Civil Liberties Union and the American Civil Liberties Union of Northern California for Leave to File Brief Amici Curiae in Support of Petition for Rehearing and Brief Amici Curiae in Support of Petition for Rehearing, (June 23, 1978)
    - 137. Certificate of Counsel [of SLM] and cover letter to the Court, (June 26, 1978)
    - 138. Motion for Leave to File Brief and Brief in Support of Petition for Rehearing Submitted by Amici Curiae [Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press et al], June 26, 1978
    - 139. Letter to Clerk of U. S. Supreme Court re error in Petition for Rehearing, (July 12, 1978)
  - Pleadings: (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 140. Order remanding cause to U.S.D.C., (July 28, 1978)
    - 141. Notice from Supreme Court re recovery for costs, (June 28, 1978)
    - 142. Cost Bill of All Defendants-Appellants, Aug 8, 1978
    - 143. Amended cost Bill of All Defendants-Appellants, Aug 11, 1978
    - 144. U.S.D.C. notification re filing of mandate of U. S. Crt. App., Aug 17, 1978
    - 145. Order [granting ACLU & Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press leave to file briefs amici curiae and denying petition for rehearing], Oct 2, 1978
    - 146. [Proposed] Judgment (Amended) (received, 6-Oct-78
    - 147. Letter "response" requesting deferment of entry of judgment from Falk, Oct 6, 1978
    - 148. Reply letter from County of Santa Clara, Oct 11, 1978
    - 149. Further letter to Judge Peckham from Jerry Falk, Nov 1, 1978
    - 150. Judgment (Amended), Nov 2, 1978
    - 151. cost Bill of All Defendants-Appellants, Nov 7, 1978
    - 152. Amended Cost Bill of All Defendants-Appellants, Nov 13, 1978
    - 153. U.S.D.C.: Notice [attaching Amended Cost Bill of All Defendants-Appellants], Nov 28, 1978
  - Publicity, 1971-1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Publicity: Stanford Daily issues, 1971-1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Supreme Court Decision, 1978 [from internet source, 1999] (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Transcript, 23-Oct-69 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Transcript, Jun 4, 1971; Sep 10, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Transcript, July 10, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Transcript, Apr 2, 1973; Jun 27, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 13)